Nicholas J. Wilson

[version date 2024.10]

PROFILE

Economist and research consultant: conflict, development economics, political economy, East Africa. I focus on themes of fragility and social cohesion, and often work with geospatial data and tools. Headed consulting engagements for UNDP, UNHCR, World Bank, IRC, IFRC, AMF, among others. Experience in China, Germany, Kenya, Netherlands, Russia, South Sudan, Turkey, UK; now Portugal.

EDUCATION

Nova School of Business and Economics

Lisbon, PT

PhD, Economics

2024-Present

· Advisor: Prof. Alex Armand

Position: Nova SBE Research Fellow

Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München

Munich, DE

MSc, Economics Grade: 1.14, Sehr Gut (Top ranked student)

2020-23

Advisor: Prof. Mathias Bühler

Visiting student: Higher School of Economics - Moscow

University of Warwick

Coventry, GB

2013-17

BSc, Economics Grade: 70, First Class Honours

Visiting student: University of Amsterdam

EXPERIENCE

Forcier Consulting

Juba, SS/Istanbul, TR

Research Manager

2022-Present

- Manage an office of 20 full-time staff conducting quant and qual research across South Sudan.
- Fielded surveys, focus groups, and interviews, and analyzed development programs and policies.
- Advised clients, trained researchers, designed sampling, managed budgets, planned logistics.

University of Massachusetts (UMass) Amherst

Remote

Research Assistant

2021-22

- Research Assistant (RA) for Prof. Lucy Xiaolu Wang, conducting research in health economics.
- Activities included literature reviews, data cleaning and analysis, managed several junior RAs.

Max Planck Institute for Innovation and Competition

Munich, DE

Research Assistant

2020-21

- RA for Prof. Lucy Xiaolu Wang, conducting research in health and innovation economics.
- Activities included literature reviews, data cleaning and analysis, management of a junior RA.

United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)

Nairobi, KE

Communications Consultant

2019-20

OC&C Strategy Consultants

London, GB

Associate Consultant

2018-19

Magic Panda International 能猫国际集团	Shanghai, CN
International E-Commerce Intern	Winter 2017

Rothschild & Co

London, GB

Investment Banking Summer Intern

Summer 2016

Lazard

London, GB

Investment Banking Summer Intern

Summer 2015

SELECTED CONSULTANCIES

Evaluation of EU Cooperation in South Sudan, 2011-23 (2024)

Contracted by Landell Mills to provide technical advice and conduct fieldwork for a major evaluation of European Union humanitarian and development assistance to South Sudan since independence.

World Bank Group 2024 Country Opinion Survey – South Sudan (2024)

Contracted by the World Bank (WBG) to administer a quantitative survey to a cross-section of the Bank's different stakeholders across South Sudan to assess engagement, attitudes, and outlook.

Scoping Study on Agriculture and Food Security Value Chains in South Sudan (2024)

Contracted by Norweigan Church Aid (NCA) to undertake a qualitative analysis of the landscape, challenges, and opportunities for agriculture value chain addition in 5 states of South Sudan.

Maternal and Child Health Baseline Study in Aweil East (2023-4)

Contracted by the International Rescue Committee (IRC) to design an experimental methodology and conduct a survey for a maternal health and newborn care programme in Aweil East, South Sudan.

Education Research in Conflict and Protracted Crises (ERICC) in South Sudan (2023-24)

Contracted by IRC to synthesize and explore education in emergencies research priorities for South Sudan through a literature review, mixed methods fieldwork, and workshops with key stakeholders.

Third-Party Monitoring of South Sudan 2022/23 LLIN Distribution Campaign (2022-23)

Contracted by the Against Malaria Foundation (AMF) to monitor planning, distribution, and verification activities for a national campaign to distribute 5.4m mosquito nets in 7 states of South Sudan.

Implementation of the UNHCR Forced Displaced Survey (FDS) in South Sudan (2022-23)

Contracted by UNHCR to implement a major global survey initiative in South Sudan assessing living conditions of IDPs, refugees, asylum seekers and returnees in camps and host communities.

UNDP Support to Devolved Governance in Kenya: Transformational Stories (2020)

Contracted by UNDP to contribute analyses and edit a narrative review of their support to implementation of the devolution process across Kenya, which included conducting fieldwork in 6 counties.

PUBLICATIONS

U.S. State Approaches to Cannabis Licensing (with Lucy Xiaolu Wang) [2022] *International Journal of Drug Policy (IJDP), 106, 103755* [IJDP]; *MPI Research Paper* [SSRN] Analysis of different state-level licensing and taxation policies for the US legal cannabis market.

WORKING PAPERS

ERICC: Towards An Evidence-driven EiE Research Agenda for South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner Tsoni, Oladele Akogun, Elifrida Twalihi, Maartje Schots, and Kur Kur Dut) [2024] *ERICC* [figshare] Synthesis and description of education in emergencies research priorities for South Sudan.

WORKS IN PROGRESS

What Works to Tackle the Out-of-school Children Crisis among Pastoralist Communities in South Sudan? (with Ioanna Wagner Tsoni, Oladele Akogun, Mohammad Faisal, and Kur Kur Dut) Qualitative study analyzing education for diverse pastoralist communities across South Sudan.

Political Economy of the South Sudan Education System (with Olha Homonchuk, Alexandra Fortacz, and Tim Kelsall)

Education sector PEA for South Sudan conducted with the Overseas Development Institute (ODI).

Conflict's Long Shadow: Evidence on Education in Emergencies in South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner Tsoni, Maartje Schots, and Ceaser Taban)

Systematic literature review identifying education in emergencies evidence gaps in South Sudan.

Hate Thy Neighbor? Conflict, Fear, and Mistrust in Kenya's White Highlands

Empirical study of long-run effects of exposure to clientelist land reforms on social discord in Kenya.

AWARDS, FUNDING, AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Nova SBE: Nova SBE Research Fellowship	2024-28
IRC: Travel funding for CIES and BAICE conferences	2024
LMU VAC: Alumni Prize for Young Economists	2023
DAAD: Scholarship for Master Studies	2020-22
Erasmus+: Erasmus Study Abroad Grant	2015-16

MEMBERSHIPS AND SERVICE

Member: British Association for International and Comparative Education (BAICE)	2024-Present
Member: Comparative and International Education Society (CIES)	2024-Present
Mentor: Malengo, Uganda-Germany Programme	2024-Present

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2024: CIES, University of Edinburgh CAS/CeSeR, ERICC/FCDO Consortium Meeting, ASAUK-Oxford Brookes, BAICE-University of Sussex

SKILLS

Quant analysis: Stata (advanced), QGIS (advanced), Python (intermediate), R (intermediate) **Qual analysis:** Natural Language Processing (NLP) in Python (NLTK) and R (Quanteda), NVivo **Field research:** design tools, program surveys, train enumerators, draft budgets, manage clients **Languages:** English (native), French (intermediate), German (intermediate), Turkish (intermediate)

PERSONAL

Citizenship: dual citizen of Ireland and the UK.

References available on request